Finding Aid for the Byron McAfee Papers LSC.0339
UCLA Library Special Collections
- II. Research papers, 1768-1964.; 16 boxes.
  - IIA. Codex studies, 1857-1961.; (4 boxes).
    - Notes, 1951.; 14 items. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Holograph and typewritten notes on tributes paid by altepetl to the Mexica, codices, and correspondence.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Excerpts, ca. 1950.; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Partial Nahuatl transcription. Bound typescript, with holograph notes in Spanish. Bound at top.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapters 1-19, ca. 1950.; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Spanish translation of original Nahuatl text; Chapters 1-19 in two parts. Bound typescript with holograph corrections.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapters 2-10, 1956.; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      First section is translated to German; middle section incomplete; last section is translated to Spanish. Bound typescript with holograph corrections.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapter 17, 1955-1956.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Bound typescript, in Nahuatl with holograph notes in Spanish.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapters 17-19, 20-23 and 24, 1956.; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Nahuatl text with Spanish translation in the following pages. Bound typescript, handwritten title "Doctrina- Dominicus."
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapter 25, 1956.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Nahuatl and Spanish. Bound typescripts with holograph annotations.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 7. Chapters 5-6, 1956.; 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Nahuatl text with complete German translation. Bound typescript with holograph notes and corrections in Spanish.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 7. Chapter 9, 1956.; 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Untranslated Nahuatl with Spanish introduction. Bound typescript.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapter 27, 1956.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Nahuatl with separate translation in Spanish. Bound typescript.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapter 29, 1956.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapter 31, 1956.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapter 33, 1955-1956.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapter 35, 1956.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapters 37-39, 40, 1956.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 6. Chapters 41-43, 1956.; 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 7. Photostat, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Photostats of the original manuscript.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 8. Photostat, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 8. Excerpts, ca. 1950.; 2 items. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Nahuatl and Spanish, with corrections. Typescript.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 9, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Photostats of the original manuscript. Corrections and notes in red ink.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de. Florentine Codex, Book 11. Chapters 7-8, 1956.; 1 item. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Spanish introductions to the Nahuatl text. Typescript with holograph annotations.
    - Sahagún, Bernardino de (?) Nahuatl vocabularies, ca. 1940.; 3 items. (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Capitulo 24: "De los castigos que hacían a los que se emborrachaban". Capitulo 27: "De los miembros exteriores y interiores ansi del hombre como de la mujer" and "de las partes del hombre y de la mujer de dentro y de fuera." Nahuatl with Spanish notes. Bound typescripts.
    - Schuller Collection lists, 1914-1920.; 4 items. (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Photostats: List of MSS at the Brinton Library (Berendt Collection) in Philadelphia, PA and at the British Museum, London, in "native languages of Latin American nations." Lists of MSS and sources on language, culture, geography, and societies in South America, including the Rudolph Schuller Collection. List of MSS at the Library of Congress.
  - IIB. Dictionaries and language, 1884-1956.; (5 boxes).
    Research papers and transcriptions related to the lingustic studies of Nahuatl and Spanish, including dictionaries and translations.
    - Vocabulario trilingüe, 1956.; 9 items. (Box 7, Folder 1-9)
      Typewritten transcript of Vocabulario trilingüe, a trilingual Spanish-Latin- Nahuatl dictionary based on Antonio de Nebrija's Vocabulario de romance en Latin of 1516, with the addition of Nahuatl equivalents. Nahuatl portions are commonly attributed to Bernardino de Sahagún.Transcription is from Ayer manuscript 1478 (Anonymous n.d.), in the Newberry Library in Chicago. Typescript is divided into nine bound sections, with one section per folder.
    - Diccionario, ca. 1950.; 13 items. (Box 8, Folder 1-12)
      Typewritten transcript entitled "Diccionario del romance al Latin por Elio Antonio de Nebrija, cronista de la Cesárea Real Majestad." Work is probably transcribed from a version of Antonio de Nebrija's Vocabulario de romance en Latin (1516), but includes Nahuatl additions. Typescript is divided into twelve bound sections, with one section per folder.
    - Molina Vocabulario, ca. 1935.; 12 items. (Box 9, Folder 1-7)
      Partial typewritten transcript of a Nahuatl to Spanish dictionary, based on Alonso de Molina's Vocabulario en lengua castellana y mexicana. Typescript is divided into seven bound sections, with one section per folder. Folder 1 includes an introduction with terms for flora and fauna of Mexico, in 5 numbered parts. Reference to Alfonso de Molina vocabulary throughout. Compares Molina spelling, modern spelling and "Nahuatlism," or Nahuatl Hispanism. Typescript is divided into seven bound sections, with one section per folder.
    - Aguirre, Porfirio. Suplemento a la clase no. 500, 1933-1934.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Course notes by Gertrudis Pignol for a Nahuatl class taught by Porfirio Aguirre. Typescript with holograph notes and illustrations.
    - La Familia, nos.1-20 (typescript), 1884.; 2 items. (Box 10, Folder 10)
      Weekly newsletter by Academia Nahuatl, containing Nahuatl grammatical lessons. Typescript, probably transcription.
    - La Familia, partial nos. 1-28, 21-46, 1885-1886.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 11)
      Nahuatl grammar excerpts from La Familia magazine. Bound.
    - Multi-lingual vocabulary, ca. 1956.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 12)
      Spanish, English, French, German, and Nahuatl vocabulary guide. Bound typescript, with holograph annotations.
    - Belmar, Francisco. Lenguas indigenas de Mexico, 1905.; 2 items. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Essays in Spanish on the Mixteco-Zapoteca language family and its relation to Otomí. Bound typescripts.
    - Cárdenas, Juan Luna. Mactizamoxtli Amapoaliztli, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Unfinished work in Nahuatl
    - Casanova, Gonzalez, P. Nota sobre la lengua Chinanteca, 1925.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Spanish essay on the Chinanteco language; excerpt from a larger published work.
    - Celtatécatl. Lecciones de Idioma Nahuatl o sea Mexicano., ca. 1920.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 5)
      Typewritten Nahuatl language lesson book, by the founder of the Nahuatl Academy in Texcoco. 52 leaves.
    - Esperanto manual, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Instruction manual by the French Society for the Propagantion of the Esperanto Language. Typescript.
    - Esperanto--Literatura Mondo, 1949.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Essay in Esperanto. Typescript.
    - Esperanto--Heroldo de Esperanto, 1956.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Essay and notes in Esperanto. Typescript.
    - Gramática Española, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 10, Folder 9)
      Excerpt from a longer published work on Spanish grammar, pp. 359-366.
    - Nahuatl geographic names, ca. 1950.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 1)
      Place names in Nahuatl, with Spanish definitions. Typescript with holograph annotations. 4 leaves.
    - Valtón, Emilio. El primer libro de alfabetizacion en America, 1947.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 10)
      Published in Mexico, D.F., by Antigua Libreria Robredo. On the first published instructional text for the alphabet and Catholic teachings. Signed by the author.
    - Nahuatl lesson book, 1920.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 2)
      Typewritten Nahuatl grammar booklet, with corrections. 71 leaves.
    - Nahuatl linguistics guide, 1944.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Spanish linguistic study of Nahuatl language compiled by a student of Lic. Avila. Bound typescript with handwritten notes.
    - Nahuatl to Spanish dictionary, C to Coztic, ca. 1950.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 4)
      Nahuatl entries with Spanish definitions; excerpt from unidentified dictionary project. Bound typescript. See box 12 for a bound Spanish translation of the introduction to Rémi Siméon's Nahuatl dictionary, and notes regarding Simeon's original translation of Alonso de Molina's Vocabulario nahuatl-castellano, castellano-nahuatl (1571).
    - Nahuatl to Spanish dictionary, In to Iz, ca. 1950.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Nahuatl entries with Spanish definitions; excerpt from unidentified dictionary project. Bound typescript.
    - Research cards, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      Photostats of Library catalog cards relating to Native American language resources.
    - Rivas, Pedro Geoffrey. Status Morfológico de las Conjunciones Nahuas, 1956.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 7)
      Essay on the morphology and syntax of Nahuatl language, written by a scholar from El Salvador. Bound typescript, 7 leaves.
    - Spanish vocabulary guide, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 8)
      Bound typescript.
    - Torres, Macario. Estudios gramaticales sobre el "Nahuatl", 1887.; 1 item. (Box 11, Folder 9)
      Published in Leon, by Tip. de J. Rivera e Hijos. Nahuatl grammar.
  - IIC. John Hubert Cornyn papers, 1926-1930.; (2 boxes).
    Typewritten drafts of articles and essays by John Hubert Cornyn, a close collaborator with Byron McAfee. Also includes correspondence documenting a gift of books and manuscripts from Cornyn to the University of Toronto (box 14, folder 11). Materials are arranged alphabetically by the title of Cornyn's work.
    - Ancient Aztec charms and incantations, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 1)
      Quotes, possibly for an English language article. Typescript.
    - How St. Helen found the Holy Cross: an Aztec comedia, 1932.; 4 items. (Box 13, Folder 10)
      Typescripts in Spanish and English. Two copies with corrections, two final drafts.
    - The lost literature of the Aztecs, 1931.; 2 items. (Box 13, Folder 11)
      Manuscript for publication (possibly Harper's Magazine). Typescript with holograph corrections.
    - Ancient Chichimeca literature, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Essay on the "incantations" and poetry recited by hunters, midwives, parents and warriors in the Nahuatl community. English, with Nahuatl vocabulary throughout. Typescript with holograph annotations.
    - Ancient Mexican literature, 1930.; 2 items. (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Drafts of an essay in English, possibly published by Harper's Magazine in 1930. Typescript with holograph annotations.
    - Aztec hero and folk tales, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 4)
      21 original short stories, based on Nahuatl culture. Includes a forward and table of contents. Bound typescript.
    - Aztec literature, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Draft essays on the linguistic, cultural and historical value of literature produced in the Nahuatl language. Typescript with holograph corrections.
    - Discovering a lost literature, 1930.; 2 items. (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - The dreamers, 1930.; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 7)
      Fiction, in English. 92 chapters. Typescript.
    - Finding a lost literature, 1930.; 3 items. (Box 13, Folder 8)
      Essay on Nahuatl text as "metered writing," and memory teaching by Nahua nobles. Includes reflections on early colonial texts by Siguenza y Gongora, Fernando de Alva Ixtlixochitl and Sahagún. Typescript with holograph corrections.
    - Grammatical analysis of an Aztec text, ca. 1935.; 1 item. (Box 13, Folder 9)
      Study of Nahuatl text in Nahuatl and English. Includes story of Quaquauh tentzone yhuan coyotl, or The goat and the coyote. Typescript.
    - The merchant (Yn pochtecatl)--Prologo, 1932.; 2 items. (Box 14, Folder 1)
      Letter from John B. Kaiser from the Oakland Library to Cornyn regarding his manuscript. Includes Spanish translation of Cornyn's introduction.
    - Tepozteco text, 1929.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 10)
      Vocabulary and notes on the summer festival of Tepoztlan in the state of Morelos, Mexico. Typescript with holograph corrections.
    - University of Toronto, 1937-1938.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 11)
      Signed letter, 1937 February 14, Mexico City, Mexico to H.J. Cody, Toronto, Ontario. Letter and related enclosures document Cornyn's gift of books and manuscripts from his personal library, many "autographed by the literary men of Mexico," to the University. Typescript, 17 leaves.
    - The worship of the kings, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 12)
      Typescript in English.
    - The merchant (Yn pochtecatl)--Transcriptions, 1931.; 7 items. (Box 14, Folder 2)
      Several draft transcriptions of the Nahuatl play from the "Andrade ms." as told by Don Joseph Gasper. Typescript.
    - The merchant (Yn pochtecatl)--Translations, 1932.; 6 items. (Box 14, Folder 3)
      Several draft versions of a Nahuatl play with an English translation and introduction by Cornyn. Typescript.
    - Nican mopohua, ca. 1935.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 4)
      The Virgin of Guadalupe's story of apparition, in Nahuatl. Typescript with holograph notes.
    - Relacion Mercuriana de la Admirable Aparición de Ntra. Sra. La Virgin Maria de Guadalupe., ca. 1940.; 3 items. (Box 14, Folder 5)
      Narrative account of the Virgin of Guadalupe's apparition, with an introduction by Cornyn. Bound typescript, 10 pages.
    - The shadow of the Gods, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Essay on Teotihuacán, and its relationship to Tula. Subtitle: "The trail of the Serpent Gods, Part II." Typescript.
    - Song of the ages, ca. 1932.; 3 items. (Box 14, Folder 7)
      Nahuatl ritual poetry, translated to English by Cornyn. Three typescripts with holograph corrections.
    - The Song of Quetzalcoatl (folder 1 of 2), 1926.; 7 items. (Box 14, Folder 8)
      Essay on, and translation of, the original Nahuatl poem of Quetzalcoatl. Includes several revisions, presumably in preparation for publication. Typescripts, with holograph annotations.
    - The Song of Quetzalcoatl (folder 2 of 2), ca. 1926.; 2 items. (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Writings related to Cornyn's translation and publication of the Song of Quetzalcoatl. Typescripts.
  - IID. Nahua history and culture, 1857-1964.; (3 boxes).
    Research papers and transcriptions related to the study of Nahua history and culture, including drama and religion. Materials are arranged alphabetacally by folder title.
    - Alva, Bartolomé de. Confesionario mayor y menor, ca. 1936.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 13)
      Confessor's guide (1634) in Nahuatl, with Spanish translation. Typescript with holograph notes.
    - Calendario Nahuatl, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 14)
      Calendar of the four systems of the Nahua and Maya. Includes a breakdown of the year count from 1583 to 2000. Entitled "La Idea, Tepoztlan, Dec. 10th, 1887 Vol I, no 24." Bound typescript.
    - Cárdenas, Juan Luna. La religión y la mitología Nahuatlakatl., 1928.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 15)
      Essay on the origin of Nahua religious stories, studied by comparing Nahua and Mestizo literature with European literature. Typescript.
    - Carlock, Armando. El llamado ancestral, ca. 1951.; 1 item. (Box 14, Folder 16)
      Poem translated from Nahuatl to Spanish by Armando Carlock, with a note from Jacobo Dalevuelta. Possibly published in El universal, 1951 October 8. Typescript, 2 leaves.
    - Congreso de Milpa Alta, 1940 August.; 3 items. (Box 14, Folder 17)
      Tabla general de conclusiones del primer congreso Azteca celebrado en Malakatepec Momochko (Milpa Alta, D.F.). Notes pertaining to the preservation of the Nahuatl culture, community and language. Text in Nahuatl and Spanish. Typescripts.
    - Conversion of St. Paul, ca. 1935.; 3 items. (Box 14, Folder 18)
      Typewritten transcription of original manuscript, written and first performed in Mexico City in 1530. Text in Nahuatl.
    - Cortes, Agustin Hunt. In Ezopo Izazanillatol: fabulas de Esopo, 1895-1929.; 5 items. (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Nahuatl to Spanish study of lexicon and syntax in Celtatecatl's Nahuatl transcription of the fable. Bound typescripts.
    - Hernandez, José N. Nombres de Lugares simbólicos en Nahuatl, del estado de Morelos y los del Distrito Federal, 1927.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 10)
      Geographic names within the Mexican state of Morelos and Mexico City in Nahuatl, with Spanish translations. Also contains translations in Nahuatl, Spanish and English of poetry, and correspondence with Roberto Carriedo, the Director of the Linguistics Center in Mexico City.
    - Hunt, Cortes y Otros. Quauhtemotzin, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 11)
      Transcription from Revista de Mexico, vol. 4 no. 33 (1890 August 17), p. 512. Text describes the Mexica Empire in the days before the fall of Tenochtitlan to the Spaniards, and the deaths of Quauhtemotzin and Coanacotzin. Bound typescript.
    - Hunting and other ceremonies, ca. 1950.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 12)
      Introductory essay in English entitled "the culture gods." On Nahua creation myths. Typescript, loose leaves
    - Memorial de los Indios de Nombre de Dios, Durango, Acera de sus servicios al Rey, c. 1563, 1942.; 3 items. (Box 15, Folder 13)
      Several transcriptions of the memorial, including: Faustino Chimalpopoca Galicia's 1845 translation from Nahuatl to Spanish; George T. Smisor's 1942 translation from Nahuatl to English; and Smisor, [Robert] Barlow, and Galicia's text in Nahuatl. Typescripts.
    - Mena, Ramón. El lienzo y la pintura de la Virgen de Guadalupe, 1932.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 14)
      Report of an inspection of the lienzo containing the original image of the Virgin of Guadalupe (1917 February 24). Discusses the work as a native painting on Maguey fiber cloth. Typescript, 9 leaves.
    - Mena, Ramón. Notas acerca de Xochicalco, 1910.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 15)
      Published article on archeological sites in Xochicalco, Morelos. Text in Spanish.
    - Mijangos, Juan de. Espejo Divino en lengua mexicana., ca. 1950.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 16)
      Nahuatl transcription of Mijango's study of the Holy Scripture, Espejo Divino en lengua mexicana en que pueden verse los Padres y tomar documento para acertar a doctrinar bien a sus hijos, y aficionallos alas virtudes (1607).
    - Motolinía,Toribio. Tres Ninos, ca. 1950.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 17)
      Citations to works by Toribio Motolinía (1568) in Nahuatl and Spanish. 1 leaf.
    - Nahuatl account of the tensions between the various altepetl of central Mexico, 1940.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 18)
      Provides a chronological account, by the Nahua calendar, of the tensions between various communities in central Mexico. Includes stories about rulers who wanted to wage battle against Nezahualcoyotl. Nahuatl with some Spanish translation. Unbound, typescript.
    - Nahuatl notes, 1945-1959.; 10 items. (Box 15, Folder 19)
      Transcription and translation of Nahuatl text to Spanish. Includes poetry and notes on sayings, death and medication. Typescript and holograph.
    - Danzas y teatro indigenas, ca. 1930.; 3 items. (Box 15, Folder 2)
      Compilation of material on folk dances and theater productions in Nahuatl from several Nahuatl speaking communities (includes bibliographic references). Typescript, handwritten notes, loose pages.
    - Nahua poetry, ca. 1950.; 15 items. (Box 15, Folder 20)
      Transcription and translation of Nahuatl poems to Spanish. Includes notes from P.F. Garcia and G. Verazaluce. Untitled. Typescript, loose leaves.
    - Escalada, Apolonio H. La Inhumanidad Castigada, ca. 1935.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Short story in the Morelos variant of Nahuatl, with Spanish translation. Bound typescript.
    - La esteril, ca. 1936.; 2 items. (Box 15, Folder 4)
      Transcription of a 16th century Nahuatl play. Bound typescript with holograph corrections. Includes a letter.
    - Galicia, Faustino Chimalpopoca. Nombres geograficos, 1857.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 5)
      Etymological and historical explanation of Nahuatl names, completed for the Boletín de la Sociedad Mexicana de Geografía y Estadística, tomo 4, no. 7. Bound typescript.
    - García, P.F. Huecayoteachcatenyotl, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 6)
      Nahuatl poem. Typescript, 3 leaves.
    - Gómez de Orozco, Federico. Dos escritoires indígenas del siglo XVI, 1930.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 7)
      Published excerpt on 16th century writers Don José Fernando Ramirez of Tlaxcala, and Agustín de la Fuente of Tlatelolco.
    - Guzman, Eulalia. Cuauhtémoc, 1955.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      Datos biograficos y cronologicos segun la historia y la tradicion de Ixcateopan. Published in Mexico.
    - Hasler, Juan A. Juan del Oso en los tuztlas, 1959.; 1 item. (Box 15, Folder 9)
      Typewritten transcription of published source.
    - Nantli, Teenan, ca. 1935.; 8 items. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      Short essays on the various members of a family (e.g. mother, child, uncle, nephew, grandmother, grandchild). Text in Nahuatl to Spanish. Typescript, loose pages arranged in consecutive order, numbered in pencil.
    - Nezahualcoyotl. The poet's song, ca. 1930.; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      English translation by John Hubert Cornyn. Typescript, 3 loose leaves.
    - Notebook (folder 1 of 2), ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 3)
      McAfee's three-ring binder with extensive typewritten and annotated text, beginning with an "indice de nombres de lugares, personas y tribus." Includes lists of names related to the history of Tlatelolco, in Nahuatl, Spanish and German. Cites Ernst Mengin's Unos annales historicos de la nacion Mexicana (1939).
    - Notebook (folder 2 of 2), 1962-1964.; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      Notebook with lined paper. Includes notes by McAfee in Spanish, English, and Nahuatl on various topics, and a draft of a letter to the President of the United States.
    - Olmos, Andrés de. El juicio final, 1932.; 3 items. (Box 16, Folder 5)
      16th century Nahuatl pastorela written entirely in Nahuatl. Typescript with holograph annotations.
    - Olmos, Andrés de. Supersticiones, ca. 1936.; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 6)
      Typewritten transcription of a work in Spanish and Nahuatl credited to Frey Olmos (ca. 1491-1570), on superstitions and beliefs in the Nahuatl culture. Bound typescript holograph annotations.
    - Olmos, Andrés de. The wise men from the East, ca. 1940.; 1 item. (Box 16, Folder 7)
      16th century Nahuatl pastorela. Translated to English with an introduction by J.H. Cornyn.
    - Passion of Palm Sunday, 1935.; 3 items. (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Transcription of Nahuatl text from Morelos document (Tepaltzinco), with annotations and translations in English. Bound typescripts.
    - Robelo, Cecilio A. Supersticiones de los Indios Mexicanos, 1907.; 1 item. (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Reprint of a published work from the Societe Scientifique, t. 26, no. 2-3.